Register of the Oleg Yadoff (Oleg Ivanovich Iadov) Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Oleg Yadoff (Oleg Ivanovich Iadov) papers
1946-1952
2001C30
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Writings, letters, and personal documents, relating to Russian émigré affairs and to the resistance movement in France during World War II.
Yadoff, Oleg, 1902-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Oleg Yadoff was born on 14 June 1902 in Rostov-na-Donu. As a young volunteer he enlisted in one of General Kornilov's shock regiments in the First World War, continuing to serve with the White Army in South Russia until its evacuation in 1920. Arriving in Yugoslavia in 1921 he resumed his education in the sciences at the University of Belgrade. Moving to France in July 1923, he received his baccalaureate in mathematics and philosophy from the Sorbonne (1925). In 1931 he received his doctorate in engineering also from the Sorbonne.
Conducting teaching and research at a variety of institutes and centers affiliated with the Sorbonne, as well as the Russian Technological Institute in Paris, he published a number of works on aeronautics and hydroelectric installations. Another doctorate in physics in 1939 was followed by a third doctorate in mathematics (1946), as well as by military service in the French air force (to 1940) and thereafter in the French Resistance (through 1945). As a recognized authority on aeronautics and fluid mechanics, from 1947 to the 1950s he was a visiting professor and research associate at Columbia University, New York, as well as consulting engineer for a number of corporations. Yadoff died in New York in 1961.
Chronology
1902 June 14 Born, Rostov-on-Don, Russia
1917 Enlisted in the Shock Regiment of General Kornilov
1918 Diploma of general studies of the secondary school at Rostov-on-Don
1920-21 Evacuated with the Volunteer Army to Turkey, Bulgaria, and Yugoslavia
1921-23 Enrolled at the Russian Cavalry School, Yugoslavia
1922 Received a university scholarship from the American Committee for the Education of Russian Youth in Exile Student, Faculty of Pure Science at the University of Belgrade
1923 July Moved to France
1925 July Bachelor's degree in mathematics and philosophy from the Sorbonne, Paris
1928 Degree in electrical engineering, the University of Grenoble
1931 Doctorate in engineering, the Sorbonne, Paris
1932-1946 Professor, Research Associate, Director of Studies at the Russian Technological Institute in France, a variety of universities and engineering schools affiliated with the Sorbonne, Paris
1939 Doctorate in physical sciences
1939-1940 Officer, French Air Forces
1940-1944 Participated in the French Resistance
1944-1945 Technical consultant, Allied Expeditionary Force
1946 Doctorate in mathematical sciences
1947-1950 Visiting Professor, Research Associate at Columbia University
? Died, United States
Scope and Content Note
Dr. Oleg Ivanovich Yadoff was an eminent engineer and doctor of engineering, physics, and mathematics, who is recognized for his studies of electrostatics and aerosols, as well as numerous achievements in aeronautics, hydroelectric installations and telecommunications. He played an important role in the French underground and was responsible for rescuing Allied aviators attached to the French Forces of the Interior.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Engineers.; France.; Russia.; Russians--France.; Russians--United States.; United States.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographical File, 1946-1952 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Article, biographical sketches, certificate, citations, clippings, curriculum vitae, letter of thanks, patent, and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  Letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, and., 1949-1952 undated (Box 1)
  One speech and several articles, arranged chronologically by title
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1946-1952 (Box 1)
  - Article about Yadoff in Book of Friendship. Franco-American Engineers' Relations. (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes an autographed offprint
  - Biographical sketches (Folder 1: 2)
  - Certificate of the Armed Forces Communications Association, 1951 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Citations
    - Air service post 501 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Medal of Freedom with Bronze Palm, 1946 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Clipping about or mentioning Oleg Yadoff (Folder 1: 6)
  - Curriculum vitae (Folder 1: 7)
  - Letter of thanks from the French government, 1946 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Patent, 1945 (Folder 1: 9)
    Method and device for projecting powders carrying electrostatic charges. Includes articles describing this method and its use in agriculture
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 10)
- CORESPONDENCE, 1951-1952
  - Ipatieff, Vladimir Nikolaevich, 1951 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Konstantinov, Petr Filaretovich, 1951-1952 (Folder 1: 12)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, and, 1949-1952 undated
  - General. (Folder 1: 13)
    Abstracts of papers presented at the meetings of the American Physical Society in 1949-1952
  - "Professor V. N. Ipatieff i sovremennye progressy khimii,", n.d. (Folder 1: 14)
    Holograph. Includes background material
  - "Témoignages: Souvenirs sur la participation des ingénieurs-docteurs dans la Résistance française," Fédération des vétérans de guerre français, 1949 May-June. (Folder 1: 15)
    Printed copy
  - "The Impact of the Physical Sciences on Engineering," Columbia Engineering Quarterly, 1950 November (Folder 1: 16)
  - "Razlozhenie molekuly gazov putem vvedenia svobodnago elektrona unichtozhaiushchego elektron stsepleniia molekuly," Rossiia, 1952 March 18 (Folder 1: 17)